<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>Alexander Klapheke</title>
		<link>https://alexklapheke.github.io/</link>
		<description></description>
		<language>en-US</language>
		<lastBuildDate>2020-06-22T07:00:34-04:00</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Foreword</title>
			<link>https://alexklapheke.github.io/blog/publish/foreword.md</link>
			<pubDate>2020-06-22T06:10:59-04:00</pubDate>
	<description>
&lt;div class=&quot;epigraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should not talk so much about myself if there were anybody else whom I knew as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a preface to this blog, let me introduce myself: I&#8217;m a linguist turned data scientist living in the Boston area. While a lot of my work deals with natural language, I&#8217;m interested in the gamut of data and what knowledge can be gleaned from it. &lt;!-- Typifying this is the current COVID-19 crisis---Massachusetts is now in the thirteenth week of a state of emergency---during which uncertainty, epidemiological data (&quot;[The Curve](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epidemic_curve)&quot;) has been exalted almost to a kind of augury. --&gt; I won&#8217;t comment much on pop data science or world events, but I hope that through reasoned analysis I can provide clarity about what data I can get hold of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I entered data science after leaving academia, but the transition wasn&#8217;t abrupt. I&#8217;d learned to code some years prior, and ran experiments as a graduate student, punctiliously collecting small data sets, modeling them in R, and encapsulating the results in manuscripts and slides. The tools I use have changed (Python largely displacing R), and the data sets are some orders of magnitude larger, but my work in graduate school laid the flagstones for a data science career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog will mainly comprise overviews of the data projects I&#8217;m working on, essays on how I approach data, particularly language data, and posts about how I use various tools&#8212;not just programming languages and text editors, but also models and theorems. I hope not only to showcase what insights can be loosed from a dataset (and what illusory insights come of unsound analyses), but also serve as an aid and reference to other data scientists&#8212;not least among whom, my future self. A full portfolio of my work can be found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://alexklaphe.github.io/&quot;&gt;my homepage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- The good news now is that, as the graph below shows, the curve seems to have peaked,[^rcode] and while it would be remiss to hazard that we&apos;re in the clear, or comment on the efficacy of this or that public health policy, I will say that I look forward to writing about my data investigations, and 

![New COVID-19 cases in Massachusetts (14-day moving average)](covid-mass.svg)\

[^rcode]: The full R code to generate this graph is below:

    ```r
    library(tidyverse)
    svg(&quot;covid-mass.svg&quot;, width = 5, height = 5)

    us_state &lt;- &quot;Massachusetts&quot;
    days &lt;- 14

    read.csv(&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/nytimes/covid-19-data/master/us-states.csv&quot;) %&gt;%
    filter(state == us_state) %&gt;%
    mutate(date = as.POSIXct(date, format = &quot;%F&quot;)) %&gt;%
    mutate(newcases = cases - c(0, head(cases, -1))) %&gt;%
    mutate(newcases_moving = stats::filter(newcases, rep(1 / days, days))) %&gt;%
    ggplot(aes(x = date, y = newcases_moving)) +
    geom_point() +
    theme_classic() +
    theme(
            text = element_text(family = &quot;Linux Libertine O&quot;),
            axis.line = element_blank(),
            panel.grid.major.y = element_line(colour = &quot;gray90&quot;)
        ) +
    labs(
            title = paste0(&quot;New cases in &quot;, us_state, &quot; (&quot;, days, &quot;-day moving average)&quot;),
            subtitle = bquote(paste(&quot;Data courtesy of the &quot;, italic(&quot;New York Times&quot;),
                                    &quot;. Updated &quot;, .(format(Sys.time(), &quot;%b %-d, %Y&quot;)))),
            x = &quot;Date&quot;,
            y = &quot;New cases&quot;
        )
    ```
--&gt;
	</description>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
